because of the scripture.
So the way we understand God's heart for the world,
and what the things that he cares about,
and therefore the things that we can care about,
and put our shoulders to the wheel on,
all of that in the scripture.
And it just helps so much become so much richer,
when we get the chance to dig in and really become aware
of that whole universe that's in the Bible.
So that's my plug.
Thank you so much for having me guys.
Thank you.
And I just want to remind the listeners that we have a great catalog
of former interviews with other fantastic folks from different walks
of life in the Orthodox world that you can go back and listen to.
And we hope you can use those to enrich your own spiritual journey
and your own communities of faith.
And until now, I'm going to be able to talk about the things that I've
of faith and until now.
next time, peace out.
[♪ OUTRO MUSIC PLAYING [♪
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever,
yor listening to ancient faithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose heart...
are troubled. All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship them, and they will praise and
bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st Denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5. The modern world
doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints. In our time,
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism, to see and to know reality
as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killer.
and dragon slayers. You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast and my co-host,
Father Stephen D'Young, is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana. And I am Father Andrew
Stephen Damick in Emmaus PA. And if you're listening to us live, you can call in. This is
actually the first episode in a while that we've taken calls live. You can call in at 855 AF
radio. That's again, that's 855-237-2346. Montesca Trudy is taking your calls tonight,
we will get to beginning in the second...
and part of our show. But first, I just wanted to mention that Lord of Spirits is brought to you
by our listeners with help from the Theoria School of Filmmaking. Theoria School of Filmmaking is
the first Orthodox film school. The primary instructor is Jonathan Jackson, a faithful Orthodox
Christian speaker, writer, and five time Emmy award winner. To learn more about Theoria, please
visit theoryoffilm.org and that's about THERI
afilm.org. So on this podcast and I endorse this product or service. There we go. Yes.
Yeah, we have sponsors, isn't that great? So on this podcast, we've talked many, many times
about the three elements of the fall of man death, sin, and domination by demonic powers.
But we've never actually dedicated whole episodes to this.
So today...
We're gonna be beginning a three-part series on this,
and our first episode is of course on death,
because that's where it starts.
That's where mankind's problems really begin.
So naturally we're headed all the way back to Genesis.
So Father Steven, is this going to be the episode
where we finally talk about how the earth
is almost exactly 6,000 years old?
No.
Oh, because that's not a thing.
But that's very disappointing.
Before we start, we have another proverbial elephant in the proverbial room.
Oh, here we go.
And I try to mind my own business, right?
Keep to my side.
Do you?
I'm not on social media, right?
But I hear things, you know?
Things get back to me.
I hear some guy Richard Rollins I guess
goes on some YouTuber show.
Starts talking a bunch of mess about how I'm a chicken.
I heard about this.
Listen up, pal.
You can hear me now and believe me later.
Nobody calls me chicken.
I know all about...
All these stories about Melchizedek.
I've read Slavonic Enek.
So I know about milk.
his adec, being born from the dead body of his virgin mother,
as the third inocic priest and being hidden even during the flood.
I know all about this.
I may have even written about it in a forthcoming book.
So Richard Rohan, if that is your real name,
here's what I want to know.
You go around acting like you know all about Ethiopia,
I haven't heard a word from you about 4-
Peruque. I don't think you even know it exists. So what now? Yeah. Yeah. We're
officially having an internet feud everybody. So join in please. Welcome. All right.
The gauntlet has been thrown down. I'm told that Richard actually doesn't even
listen to this live. So he doesn't even know what a hundred people now know about him. So yeah.
Yeah, I have no doubt he's gonna he's gonna need a lot of time
Yeah, exactly.
If you.
Yeah, but so on to our topic for tonight.
And with with apologies to our listeners that they had to sit through that kind of nonsense.
But sometimes you have to respond to some.
I'm sorry you guys had to hear that.
But you know, they're saying stuff.
So things have to be said in return.
Yeah, you can't just let some of these things slide.
Yeah, no matter how obscure a person it is who says it.
so
And we're going to begin this evening as we begin so many evenings by doing a little recap,
right, because we're going back to the Garden of Eden. We're talking about the expulsion from Paradise.
We're talking tonight about death coming upon the human race. And so as with several of our episodes
recently, these aren't things that we've never talked about before, but we're kind of coming at it
from a different trajectory tonight.
Yeah, and so just to remind people because
even if you have recently listened to all of the previous episode straight through
Because you've been lost at sea or something with an iPhone. I don't know
It's been probably about a hundred hours since the last time we talked about this minimum. So
We need to
Go over...
a couple of themes from Genesis 1 and Genesis 2 respectively.
So as we've talked about a couple of times in a couple of different episodes in the past,
in Genesis 1, part of the structure of the description of the six days of creation,
followed by the seventh day is that this follows the general pattern of temple
construction. And we'll probably end up wrapping around and doing another temple episode and going into this and even more detail again.
Yeah, but I'll be good on temple construction narratives stories of gods, temples being built or them building and then coming to inhabit their temples.
that's a major genre of ancient Near Eastern literature.
And so Genesis 1 has
has those features. And as I said at some point we'll probably go more to have
than that. There's also there are continuities and discontinuities with the
other ancient Near Eastern examples. But the key element for tonight is that at
the end of creation being constructed as the temple of Yahweh, the God of Israel,
that the Sabbath day when he comes to rest, it's not that he needs a break.
or he's tired, it's that he is seated, he is enthroned.
Right, which we covered a lot in our ascension episode from last year.
We talked about this. Yeah. Yeah.
So that is an important element to kind of have back in your mind for what we're going to talk about tonight.
And the second kind of element, and this is something we've mentioned, I know repeatedly.
so this is maybe a little...
little fresher is the pattern in Genesis 1 and 2 of you see this in the creation days,
the first three days are things being put in order, the second three are then being filled
with life.
And then the garden itself, a garden is sort of the perfect combination of the two, right?
without life is sort of just barren and life without
order is the buy you next door to where I'm speaking to you from right now.
Can you go fishing there? There must be some kind of something, something good in there.
Yeah, an alligator might catch you, but, um, well, so, uh, no guts, no glory, right? Yeah. Yeah.
Um, I have a producer now who gets a alligator farming. Um, so, and then that, that, uh, pattern of creation,
being putting things in order and filling them with life is then what is handed down to humanity to continue that work
By filling the earth and subduing it right filling it with life and subduing it putting it in order
And we've talked before about how
One of those tends to the masculine the other to the feminine and that men and women
Participate together to accomplish both right right
Okay.
So that's the quick recap.
So if we have those kind of things in the back of our head,
that will help as we now go forward.
Yeah.
So this is the beginning of, as you mentioned,
sort of a three part series.
Yeah.
And these are going to be patterns somewhat the same way.
So in our first half of the three tonight.
We're going to be talking about the way in which Angelic or Divine beings get involved in
this first fall of man. Because each of the three, obviously we already did our five-ish falls
of the Angel's episode way back in the long ago time. Now we're focusing on the human side,
but there are in each of these three there are angelic beats.
who get involved. Right. And since this is the first one, and this is the one that immediately
follows the creation of the world, those stories, we need to start by talking a little bit about
the invisible creation. Right. Because we understand, and it's even referenced in the nice
that creation has these components visible.
and invisible. Right. And the whole premise of the show is about reuniting those, right?
But when we talk about the creation of the world and the way a lot of folks, especially in
our modern era, sort of the modernist approach to these things, focus is almost entirely on
the material element of that, which is why some folks, you know, spend their time plumbing
the depths.
of the age of the earth and where dinosaurs fit into Genesis and these sort of things,
because they're primarily concerned with the scientific material elements. But the elements of
the invisible creation are important here. The other thing that tends to happen,
and I'd probably feel worse about bashing John Milton if he weren't a Puritan.
And he's dead.
I mean, he's not gonna bug by this.
So he's dead pure.
Yeah, he'd write exactly.
Um, so some very nice poetry though.
I know.
Yeah.
Hey, I spent a lot of time, I was to say, I spent a lot of time with, um, especially 16th
and 17th century English poetry as an undergrad.
And so I have a very soft spot in my heart for that stuff.
Yeah.
Milton's mighty line.
you know?
Right? Milton's my line, yeah.
I prefer the content still.
So, but from...
I mean, you have to give him credit, right,
that his writing was sort of so powerful, that everyone now has this sense
that there was some kind of primordial, not only creation of angelic beings
before the creation of the world.
Never
disgust in the Bible, but there was this war in heaven before the creation of the world.
That that has just become so commonplace as a belief.
Right.
I mean, he took stuff that is either in or implied in Scripture and kind of projects it
backwards to before Genesis 1-1.
This stuff all happens off camera and then you get paradise lost.
Right.
Yeah.
Yeah, right, but we need to take seriously that Genesis 1 and 2 are giving us the story
of creation.
Yeah, and angel created.
Not of the creation of matter, not of the creation of the visible world, but of creation,
the whole thing.
The whole creation.
that the visible and the invisible creation are not sort of these
in two separate compartments. Again, the whole theme of the show,
right? In these two separate compartments and don't interact, like there's some kind of invisible
dimensional wall between us and Heaven, and the angels are up there doing stuff, and we're here.
So the question because if we accept that, so if we accept okay, what we have in
Genesis 1 in particular, and the beginning of Genesis 2, is the creation of all of creation,
visible and invisible, then where within the narrative of Genesis, where does the invisible
creation fit in?
Yeah, because it doesn't seem to be explicit anywhere in there, you know, and on the
God created the angelic beings. Right. Yeah. Right. It's up.
explicitly. Right. Right. Right. And so what you tend to get is, and if you read Second
Temple Jewish sources, if you read the church fathers on this, they will generally peg it
to one of the creation days. Okay. So they don't see it as this separate event outside of
the narration of Genesis 1.
Yes, not day zero.
Right, but they also don't, there's no gap theory, right? Yeah. So, um,
Tales of the Crypt demon knight is not accurate. Um, huh?
I know that's where you were getting.
You know me was from. Yeah.
That stuff I, you know, when I was a kid, I saw that that stuff existed,
but it always uged me out on a very, very deep level.
Tell some of them.
night. Yeah, I mean, I didn't even know that there was, I just
news tales from the crypt existed. I didn't know that there was
even a demon night. No, it is the first and you should watch
what you say about it, because J. D.
P.
Kit Smith is in it. And if anybody hears you say to think bad about
that movie, you can get smacked. I have nothing to say about
the movie. I've never. I'm just saying.
Don't even want to mention her name.
It's not, you know, it's not like Tolkien fans who have
everything to see about.
shows that haven't even come out yet. Yes, right. And stars Billy Zane before he went bald,
but ironically he shaved his head in it. Anyway, so it's inaccurate. That's the right. Right.
So not a bad movie, but inaccurate much better than the sequel, which start Dennis Miller.
that Dennis Miller really?
Yes.
Okay.
Tales from the grip.
to board an elo of blood.
Yeah, I'm still not gonna watch it, but oh gosh.
No, it's not.
Where he, the spoilers, he ends up shooting a bunch
of vampires with holy water in super soakers.
Okay.
Well, all right.
As one does.
So moving on is also an accurate
as you know from our Halloween episode this year.
Yes, right.
That is not how vampirism works or any of that stuff.
Yeah.
So, right.
so that the second template is sure.
and the fathers see this somewhere in the framework of the creation days.
Right? So usually, not always, but usually it's either the first day or the third day.
Okay, so why would they pick those days?
Or the fourth day, I'm sorry, the fourth day.
Yeah. So why would they pick those days?
Well, first day light is created.
The fourth day is the sunroon and stars, which as we talked about,
connected biblically to the angels.
Right.
Yeah, you wouldn't want to create those things and just...
them float out there without an angel to take care of them.
Right.
Yeah.
So usually one of those two days, the minority report is there's some second day.
And I think the second day folks are are looking at the separation of the waters above from
the waters below and they're looking at that as the creation of heaven.
in the heavens, right?
Okay.
So that's sort of the...
minority report. But that's the heavenly hosts. Right. So those are the and and this is true, even for
fathers, for example, like St. Augustine, who don't hold to like 24 hour days in sequence.
Right, so say to Guston famously, believe.
that time doesn't apply to God. So this sort of all happened at once. And the days there are
just sort of a structure to explain it to us. Yeah, a literary structure rather than a chronological
structure. Right. And so there are certain other fathers who have similar, not say Augustine's
exact view, but who talk about Genesis 1 as being a structure for explaining it to us,
rather than being a literal blow-by-blow account.
Yeah, it doesn't, if I recall correctly, doesn't same basal.
Is it in the hexameron who kind of says, look, we don't know exactly.
And it's not super important that we know these kinds of things.
Right.
That like that beyond what's in that, that what is told to us in the text.
We don't have a capacity to know.
Right.
Yeah.
It's, you know, that that that's left to God.
But so we need to be attentive to what he did tell us and what he's teaching us by it.
And he was using that I think to sort of cut
off speculation, right, right, can run all over the place. Yeah. Yeah. And that kind of approach
generally makes sense because if we take also take seriously the idea that we find in most of the
fathers, I'm not going to give a percentage, but most of the fathers who talk about it, that the
The Prophet Moses received this in a vision.
Right.
Yeah, right. It seems to me if he received it in a vision and you're going to be a stickler for like literal 24 hour days
then he must have been like standing there on Mount Sinai
for six or seven straight days watching playing it all that vision happened. Yeah. So yeah, I can't probably can't pause it
It being a visionary experience. There's going to be symbolism. There's going to be right
to communicate things that aren't necessarily
literally. Now, right, and non-literal. Yeah, and you know, and why would they say that Moses
received this in a vision? Well, because Adam and Eve were not taking notes. And of course, they
also weren't present for most of what's in the, in the, you know, so this would have to have been
revealed by God to Moses who writes Genesis. Right, right. Yeah, right. So that's that's
idea. And again, we're not saying it's not literal. We're just saying it's perfectly reasonable to
take a symbol.
of what's going on there, especially what we're talking about,
Genesis 1.
Is it a symbolic world?
I don't know.
That sounds big.
So there is the key though here.
The key thing that we can say that is taught because we've said
there's these differences and distinctions and nuances, right?
stinctions and nuances, right? But the key thing.
that's taught here is that the visible and invisible creations are a product of the same creative act.
Right, because the idea that they are kind of two utterly separate creations is
simply not a thing in scripture. And as you said, it's mentioned in the creed,
you know, that he created all things visible and invisible. Yeah, you know, it's just creation. Yeah,
Yeah, right.
Um, so this and again we, we, we,
obviously we talked about this again in the before time in our episode about the five
ish falls of the angels but that then of course raises the question of the falls of angels
and specifically the devil.
Yeah.
So what you find when you start, right, looking this up is that often there's either,
either spoken of.
as if no real amount of time passed between the creation of angelic beings and them at
least beginning to fall.
Yeah.
If I recall correctly, isn't it St. Maximus maybe who says that they fell or maybe he's
talking about Adam, but the ICA, that's where they fall as they come into being.
Right.
Well, that's what I was about to say is that you find father saying the same thing about
humanity.
Yeah, right.
Right. Right. Right. Right. Because there there is no again, within the story and Genesis, there is no time lapse.
Right. Like we don't have, you know, five years later, you've was standing next to the tree of the knowledge of good eating right. Like right. Right.
There's no indication of how much yeah of when things. I mean, there's an order a sequence, right. But there's no indication of how long it takes from one thing to the next.
Right, right, and I think we need to understand.
understand that, as we've talked about so many times, you don't know what it's like to
be a bat, you don't know what it's like to be a vast cosmic intelligence. You don't even
know what it, what it's like to be a newly created human in the presence of God and paradise.
I mean, I can't remember being born. So, yeah. Right. And so we don't know in the same way
that we don't know how we will experience time in the life of the world to come.
We tend to think about it as if time, we're going to experience time the same way we do now.
It's just going to be like forever. It's going to be an endless succession of moments.
But there's no logical reason to believe that.
Right. That's how we're going to experience time.
And the same thing is true before the expulsion of paradise.
Right. And so I think one of the things that's
It's really important to highlight here when we talk about
about the fall of the devil, right?
And we're talking about the fall of human beings too, right?
So this is, you know, kind of just using the word fall
in this context.
Yeah, exactly.
Often fall within a certain theological framework
is used to mean flipped the switch from good to evil,
right?
At this point, you know, this, you know, it's unfallen.
and he was perfect soon.
this, whatever. And then the switch gets flipped and it's evil, depraved, damned, right?
You know, but that is not really the way that the scripture and traditional Christian
theology use this term. It's actually a little bit more literal in some level, or maybe
say a little bit more analogical. It's more about being thrown out, cast down, right?
you know so for
instance, you know, when when Christ says they see Satan fall from heaven, that's this
analogical sense of being thrown out and falling down.
Not it doesn't mean turning to evil because presumably there's already evil present within
the serpent before he's cast out from paradise, right?
And we certainly know that Adam and Eve have already transgressed against the Lord before
they're cast out from paradise.
So it's not the same thing as turning
to evil, kind of flipping a switch and no longer being good.
It's really about being thrown out, is the sense of fall.
Right, right.
So there's, there are actions taken, those actions have consequences.
One of those is a falling and being cast out in expulsion, right, a removal.
And then that in turn has consequences.
Yeah.
Right.
So yeah, we've got the heavy weight of St. Augustine in Western culture, right?
Wailing on us with this, right, where he kind of condensed the three falls we're going
to be talking about these three episodes to just the one we're talking about in this
episode and where this is humanity becoming evil or depraved.
Yeah.
Right.
And as we're going to see tonight, that's not what this story is about.
And as we go through the next couple of episodes, we'll see how other elements of that come
into play in the biblical narrative.
but yeah, and we're also especially as modern.
especially as modern.
Western folks, very much in the sort of good guy, bad guy mode.
Yeah, it's a pretty reality, right?
Yeah, and we should also say, even though we are dividing this into three discrete episodes
on death, sin, and demonic domination, there's kind of a lot of overlap that happens between
these things.
So we can talk about them as separate events.
can talk about them in separate concepts. But they...
They're really intimately connected as I think will become apparent as we move through this progression, right?
Right and
Yeah, we have this we have this good guy bad guy thing so it's you know Adam and Eve are good people
Then they become bad people then they're bad
Right and then Kane who will talk more about next time he's a bad person
Yeah, there's good angels and bad angels
Right and there's the cowboy with the white hat and the black cat
Right then Johnny Cash shows up and you get all confused right good guys wear black
so and yeah and
There aren't like good people and bad people there aren't good guys and bad guys there's a bunch of guys
All these dudes they do good things and they do bad things
But more on that in our third half. Yeah, so
So yeah.
So accepting that, right, so the creation of the angelic beings happens somewhere in Genesis
one, right?
Don't really feel a need to plant a flag, right, but somewhere in there.
And it's been commented on frequently, right?
We have sort of, well, if you're a modern biblical scholar, you say, we have two conflicting
of creation in Genesis 1 and 2.
Yeah.
Or maybe the people who put these things together thought they went together.
Maybe it's been circulating in the way it currently is for like thousands of years now
and nobody's had massive problems with it.
But anyway.
So the usual way in which interpreters who are attentive to such things deal with...
with this is that they talk about how, right?
We're told at the end of Genesis 1 that humanity is created,
God creates the male and female, right?
And that's sort of it, right?
Yep.
And then in Genesis 2, it's like we zoom in now.
Note to our zoomer listeners.
When I say zoom in, I do not mean connect a zoom call.
Now this is like the day lenses.
Yes.
Back in the day with
And we had cameras that were not part of our phones.
There was a lens on that camera that you would have to focus
and which you could, some of them were zoom lenses
that would allow you to make things look larger
that were far in the distance.
And I'm using zoom in in that sense.
Thanks, Dad.
Antiquated technology.
So, so Genesis 2 is sort of Zoom.
in on the creation of humanity and telling that story in more detail.
Yeah, right. So as we're about to say that the fall of the devil,
the devil being cast down, right, happens in Genesis 3,
we are not disagreeing with those fathers who don't have a separate span of time.
Yeah, yeah, these are just different angles for trying to understand.
what's going on. Right. We're saying that just like Genesis 2 zooms in on the creation of man,
Genesis 3 is zooming in on this first fall of humanity and on the fall of the devil,
which may very well have happened back during Genesis 1, the same way the creation of humanity is
described in Genesis 1 originally. So we're not disagreeing there. It's not that well the fathers say
they fell originally and those priests on Lord of Spirit.
are saying it happened four days later. That's not a thing. But so this is, and that again,
right, I know we belabored this back in the day,
Contra Milton, that the devil falls here not sometime before creation, but
but as we...
mentioned at that time, St Andrew of Cessaria sort of lays this out in his commentary on
revelation. Yeah, which talks about the casting out of the devil. Right. He gets, he gets
revelation 12. And we're going to talk about revelation 12 more here in a few minutes,
but he gets a revelation 12 that talks about the dragon and a third of the stars and
St Michael casting him down. Yeah. Yeah. And we're going to talk about the other issue he
deals with but he talks about.
when the fall of the devil happened and we're going to quote from, we talked
before, I've already pushed it at people who've pointed out to me that it's very
expensive, but what can you do?
That ancient face own Dr. Genie Constantino, her dissertation was on St. Andrew
Cessery as commentary and on the reception history of the book of Revelation in
in the Eastern churches in general.
It's sort of mad hysterical.
we're actually magisterial on that topic.
And in the process, she also made her own translation
of St. Andrew's Commentary on Revelation
that's included in the Fathers of the Church Series
from, I think Catholic University of America
publishes that.
But that sounds right.
One of those blue books.
So, yeah.
So just to keep it in the ancient faith family.
There you go.
Oh yeah.
So yes.
So here's what St. Andrew says about this, quote,
one must know
that as it has been given to the fathers, after the creation of the perceptible world,
this one had been cast down on account of his pride and envy, he to whom had first been
entrusted the aerial authority just as the Apostle said.
End quote. So that's St. Andrew of Cisria saying it happens.
That's the last bit about being entrusted the aerial authority as the Apostle said.
is talking about St. Paul referring to him as the prince in power of the air.
Yeah, yeah.
Right, so I mean there's and then of course then you have there's a few other
Scriptural references to the double being cast out or falling right
Right aside from Genesis 3 and yeah, yeah, so you've got in Isaiah 14
This is and we've referenced this before. This is the the biblical
account of what's often called the succession myth in studies of mythology
verses 30.
through 15, this is, you know, the prophet or God, I think, speaking to the devil, right,
saying, you said in your heart, I will ascend to heaven above the stars of God. I will set my
throne on high. I will sit on the mount of assembly in the far reaches of the north. I will ascend
above the heights of the clouds. I will make myself like the most high, but you are brought down to
shield to the far reaches of the pit. So ambition fall. Right.
paying the mount of assembly, right? The mountain where the divine council meets as being in the far
reaches of the north is hammering home that this is speaking about bail. Yeah, identifying bail is the
devil in particular on mountain's a phone, which literally means the mountain of the north.
Yeah. So another one then is in Ezekiel chapter 28. This is verses 13 through 17. And this one
speaks about the devil specifically as a throne.
in paradise, right? So starting with verse 13, you were in Eden, the garden of God. Every
precious stone was your covering, sardious, topaz and diamond, barrel, onyx and jasper,
sapphire, emerald and carbuncle, and crafted in gold were your settings and your engravings
on the day that you were created. They were prepared. You were an anointed guardian cherub.
I placed you. You were on the holy mountain of God in the midst of the stones of fire you
walked. You were blameless in your ways from the day you were created till unrighteousness
was found in you in the abundance
of your trade, you were filled with violence in your midst and you sinned. So I cast you
as a profane thing from the mountain of God. And I destroyed you, a guardian, Cherub, from
the midst of the stones of fire. Your heart was proud because of your beauty. You corrupted
your wisdom for the sake of your splendor. I cast you to the ground, exposed you before
kings to feast their eyes on you. So you got God throwing them out from Eden, from the
mountain of God. Right, right, and yeah, and so if he's still...
still walking on high in Eden, right? This is, again, pointing us to Genesis 3 is the place
where this happens, right? And so that brings us sort of back to Revelation 12, and
saying Andrew Cessery is commentary on it because what he's trying to deal with in Revelation
12, particularly in Revelation 12, verses 7 and 8. It describes
Saint Michael throwing the dragon out of heaven with his angels, but it describes
that right after it describes the birth of Christ.
Yeah.
Which, and so that's why he says, you know, well we know that he was cast down after the
creation of the world, right?
In Genesis 3, we've received that from the fathers, they received it from, you know, the
apostles and from Christ.
So.
We know that's so what's going on here, right?
How was this happening after?
After the birth of Christ, right?
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, so you've got two options.
You either got the devil who is one being falling two times, which again strongly shows
that position was strongly so that this isn't about turning to evil.
It's about being thrown out, right?
or there's the possibility that these are two different beings entire
one is cast out in Genesis 3 and then another one is cast out after the birth of Christ.
Right. Because St. Andrew connects this after the birth of Christ to Luke 10, verse 18.
Right. Where Christ says, I saw Satan fall like lightning. I saw Satan fall like lightning.
That's during his ministry, right? He's describing what's going on during his ministry. He says,
that's the other one. So you can also
read, and this is part of why St Andrew describes these these two options. It talks about the
dragon, the literal wording in Greek is the dragon who is the devil and Satan. Well, there's
two ways to read that and. Right. You can say the dragon who is the devil and Satan, right?
as in all three of those are names for the same
critter, right?
or you can read that as the dragon who is the devil and Satan, this other guy. Right. And so because Luke 10 specifically mentions Satan, right?
It's possible to read it as, okay, the devil falls in Genesis 3 and then Satan is cast out
of heaven.
The Satan who's still sort of hanging around in God's throne room in the book of Job is
cast down.
during Christ's ministry. You can read it that way. That's not how St. Andrew reads it. St. Andrew
reads it as they're the same being and he falls in two different senses. That's how St. Andrew understands
it. This is one of those things we've kind of talked about this a little that there are
sort of a number of devil figures.
It's a good temple literature and who are referenced in...
in the canonical scriptures. And you know, we can let you know, the devil Satan,
a Zazel, a Zazel, Boliol,
Bastima,
Bastima.
And then there's other forms that he's like Satana, Alan stuff, but Sam,
so you have these sort of different figures but nobody says none of
those sources say that there are six different beings. Yeah.
They always have one or two beings, like two at most. And then they
position those names around those beings in different ways.
Right. So there are some things that have a zeal being the serpent
in the Garden of Eden. And the being we're going to talk about next
time in terms of the daughter of man, but then maybe have satan as a
different being.
So there's all these different.
So, and as we've talked about before,
the demonic by nature are beings of chaos and destruction
and lies.
The fact that it's not easy to lay it all out,
it should not be surprising in any way.
Right.
So, but so now that we've talked about those other places,
sort of back to Genesis 3,
and we've talked about this in the five-ish falls
the angels way back when.
But the devil comes and he temps humanity to join him sort of in his rebellion and we're
going to expand what rebellion means in this context here in a minute.
And then in response, he's thrown down.
Now a lot of people read this as if it were a Rudyard Kipling just so story right here
now.
The devil.
Here's how the snake lost his legs like snakes used to have legs.
Right.
I think I've seen like children's books.
It was...
I just traded children's books.
I'm reaching way deep down into the depths of my half subconscious,
but I really feel like that's true.
I feel like that's true.
I saw kids' books with snakes with legs,
and then at the end, you see no legs on them.
Yeah, this is how Brontosaurus has turned into snakes.
No, that's not what it's talking about.
So, we talked before about the Cherubim connection
and Ezekiel that we just heard the Throne Guardian,
Sarov.
being the Egyptian word for serpent, the Seraphim being sort of the same role, but in an Egyptian
context as opposed to a Mesopotamian context, all of that kind of thing. But the word
was thrown out to crawl on the ground, right? The word there are, we've talked about before,
that word is used relatively frequently, not just in the Old Testament, but in the other
cognate word in other Semitic languages to refer to the underworld.
Right?
So this is him being ca-
down to the underworld and we've also talked about how and this is something that always needs
to be re-interrated. Ancient people weren't stupid. Right?
Because we have all our technology and stuff that people in the ancient world were just dumb.
Right. And computers and science and rockets. Yeah.
Yeah.
So, uh, this...
This is not the case.
And unless you're a person who could build their own iPhone
from scratch, you don't have anything
to brag about over exit people in terms of technology.
But the point being in this case,
that they didn't think that snakes ate dirt.
Right.
It's a symbolic way of describing him.
like, you know, we see that Adam is made out of dot.
and we see now he's cursed to return to dust.
And if the snake is eating dust,
that's the same word.
Right, exactly.
It's essentially the first is apart.
Right, right.
It's now the hell mouth.
Now it's the underworld that swallows up the dead.
Right, which is depicted in a lot of iconography,
this massive reptilian mouth
that is the place where the dead go.
And of course, in the resurrection crisis,
just pulling up up out of there.
But yeah, and of course, then you've got Hebrews 2.14, which explicitly says that the devil is the one who holds the power of death was.
Yeah, it was. Yeah, right. By that point.
But yes, yeah. And so that's that's, he's hurled down. He gets sort of, you know, you get to dwell among the dead, right?
going to Sheol as we talked about with Sheol not a happy place not a fun place to
be. They don't have good parties there. That it's not sort of pleasant. Again, this is,
gotta get that Milton right out of your head, right? This idea that it's some kind of kingdom
that the devil rules or something, that he'd rather rule and hell than serve in heaven
and da da da da da da da. If you're up here and you really don't like kings, then people
with the ambition to be kings.
But the reality is that the devil is hurled there.
The devil is imprisoned there just as much as everybody else.
Yeah. Right.
Um, which is part of why the devil is depicted the way he is in, for example,
the icon of the heroine of Hades.
Right.
You notice he doesn't have like a crown or a weapon.
Something on the ground.
That's it. He's not like he had a fight with Christ and lost, right? He's like an old
naked man. Yeah, just gets sort of flattened. Yeah, it's very different than the image that
you tend to have from pagan literature, where you know, like there's the idea that Hades
is the God who rules and is in charge of, you know, and has people, you know, of the underworld.
And it's pretty pathetic by comparison.
And if you compare him, if you look...
at an icon of the Heron of Hades, compare the way he's depicted in Hades to the way the old
Testament saints are depicted in Hades. And you'll notice something, unlike him, they all have
nice clothes. Something to think about. Yeah. So he, but he's actually worse off than them than the
the he's in Hades, right?
He's not in charge.
So.
The last thing then that we want to talk about here in the first half is as I mentioned
sort of what is the nature of the devil's rebellion?
Okay, because again our friend Milton, right?
We have this idea that well, and not this I can't totally blame on Milton because this
of course ultimately comes from the succession myth.
Hmm right from the pro devil propaganda of the neighbor
nations, which uniformly says that, no, this guy, this storm God, whether it's
bail or Zeus or whoever else, no, he successfully went and killed slash defeated slash displaced
the most high God and set himself up as the most high God.
Right.
That's what all they present him is staging this successful revolution.
to make himself king of the gods, right?
And so I'll be fair to Milton because I've been picking on him.
Right.
I'm thinking this is where he got his understanding of what the devil's rebellion is.
But we don't need to buy into his propaganda because the reality is if you think about it
for very long, right?
And I've said this to people when talking about it in person.
I've just looked at it person said, okay, like the devil, you are a creature.
are going
to make God, not be God anymore, and make yourself God and get his, I guess, God powers or whatever.
How are you? You're looking at this. How do you do that? What is step one of your work?
Yeah. Right. And, you know, I think that that comes, the reason why the pagan story works as a
story is because their most high God is inherently way less.
right, then Yahweh, the God of Israel, Father, Son and Holy Spirit.
Right.
Like their image of what the most high God is is that he's sort of the biggest and baddest
of them, right, rather than the one who is outside of all things and the creator of all
things, the Lord of heaven and earth, you know, which is why you get this polemic throughout
the scriptures about our God being and being all those things.
He's having an, you know, in heaven and earth.
He's above all gods.
He's no one's like him at all.
right, but the most high God in pagan mythology almost picked one you picked which whatever
one you like as big and bad as he is. He's they don't even claim that he's like the father
of center Holy Spirit. Yeah, and usually maybe yeah, usually the current most high God not only did
he overthrow the last guy, but he's usually at least the third. Yeah, right. Right. Most high God
going back. There's usually been several successions and these gods come into being at some point.
and then can die and be replaced and succeeded by others. Right. Yes. And so these are not,
these are not remotely, you know, the true God because we're talking about actual God, the
Holy Trinity, that dog don't hunt. It's not possible. Yeah. You can't not a way to do it.
kick cut off it. It's like saying I'm gonna knock this guy out.
Yeah, you can't be like a doctor doom on battle world and build your harness and suck
black. This is powers.
Right. Galactus, the eater of worlds.
Yes. Yes.
Who's the silver still got owned by beyond or anyway?
So I'm that's true.
I remember that I remember.
Uh, what was that that?
Oh, secret war.
It was supposed to be a secret.
So I'm.
Yeah.
Secret words.
Back in, I think that was in the late 80s, early 90s, maybe.
Yeah.
Wasn't it?
Boy, boy.
Wait, wow, that's all.
long time ago. Deep old cuts here, everybody. Yeah. Yeah. So you can, you can, if you're
step one, when I asked that question, was build a power cosmic siphon? Not going to work for
you. Right. So this isn't a possible thing. Right. Right. And it's not like, well, maybe
the devil thought it was a possible thing. Like for how many fractions of a second, what
he have thought that right.
I mean, you used the intelligence.
Remember, yeah, you get
I mean, you get this language in scripture where it says,
you know, you said in your heart, I will, you know,
sit on the mount of assembly and, you know, I will,
I will be above the stars of God.
I will set my throne on high.
But, you know, you notice that's how I'm talking about God.
Yeah, right. It's like, well, it's other angels,
the other creatures. Right. Right. Right.
I'll make myself like the most I.
So he doesn't even say I'm going to really knock the most
high off his throne. It's just sort of, I will be
Like him, you know.
but no. No, right. Yeah, right. You can't you can't actually do that. I mean you get I mean we talked about this
I don't remember I think it is way way early on we talked about St. Gregory the great talking about
how it is that the the demons you know de-throne God and he says that they de-throne him in their minds
essentially meaning that they
Decide they're not going to obey him anymore, that they're putting themselves on the throne of their
own minds. It's the idea. I mean, it doesn't remove God from his throne. It's just sort of a choice
about the way you're going to exist. And this is why we did part of that recap that we did.
Right. Because remember, Eden is a temple, right? Paradise is a temple in this sense. Adam
is a priest in this temple.
So what is the devil trying to do when he talks to Eve?
Trying to get
humanity to be faithful to him and to serve him and essentially to worship him
Even he consisting of food, right?
Worship him in the temple of God. Yeah, he's trying to set up idolatry and
and you serve that temple.
In the world.
In the sense, which you can do,
because humans can do the wrong thing.
Right.
And so what he's trying to do,
he can't destroy God.
Yeah.
Right?
That's not a thing you can do.
But he can try to destroy God's other creations.
and he chooses humans for a-
particular reason because this word keeps coming up, right?
We heard it in St Andrew.
We heard it in some of the Old Testament passages.
This word envy.
Yeah, the devil fell out of envy that this that his pride is
connected particularly to envy, right?
It's not just pride in a general sense, but connected
particularly to envy.
So envy of who and about what?
Well, this is envy of humanity.
Because humanity already has.
And this is what we're going to be talking about for most of the rest of tonight.
Already had a destiny for which he was created by God that is a destiny that the angelic beings,
even the high-ranking ones, did not share.
Right?
And so the devil is glorious a creature as he was.
Right? It was going to end up less glorious than humanity.
Right.
And so he he wants that.
And out of envy and jealousy and pride because he has no way to do anything to God.
And he has no way to change it so that he will have that destiny.
Right.
He chooses to try to destroy the human creatures who do.
Yeah, so that they don't get there.
And that they follow him into his misery.
Right.
Because it loves company.
So you should start a company and make...
misery. Anyway, and so this, when we talk about this destiny, we're talking about, so when
you read, for example, St. Dionysius the Aereopigites, celestial hierarchies, right, we've talked
about this before on the show, the angels don't sort of have species. Right. Right.
right?
I'm sorry if I'm chair of them because they don't reproduce.
Right?
They don't.
Right.
So in a certain sense, every angelic being is unique.
But in another sense, they have these ranks,
right, these orders of angelic beings.
And those orders are particular roles they play, right?
Particular jobs they do in terms of God's rule and administration of the cosmos.
He doesn't need them to do it any more than he needs humans.
but he created the
and us out of love, right, to share his divine life with and to share his rule with. And so,
what you find in St. Dionysius is that depending on that role, where they stand in that hierarchy,
what role they have, what order they are in, they participate in the grace of God
in God's actions and humanity.
And that's what separates the rank.
or orders from each other, they participate to a greater or lesser degree, right, in his,
in his energies and his grace and his power, right? And so they participate in God's grace
in a way that's not totally dissimilar from what we talk about when we're talking about
about fiosus in humans.
Right, when we talk about humans experiencing salve-
experiencing theosis we talk about them, drawing closer to God, participating in God's grace,
participating in his energies which are his work in the world, what he is doing in the world,
humans participate in it. But there's a major difference in that the angels, the angelic beings
participate in God's grace and his power in a static way based on their role.
And yeah, they're made for this, they participate in...
in God for this. And they're not going to get promoted or move up there like yeah, you know,
yeah, you don't start out as an angel and then you know you go and help George Bailey and get
your wings and then, you know, you sort of rank up. Yeah. Yeah. Some day I can I want to be a
dominion. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Yeah. You did a great job, you know, as as a cherubim. So we're making
you a serifim right that's not that's not how
works, right? So there's this, it's static, right? And so the same was true of the devil before his
fall. Yeah. This is what prompts this envy and this jealousy. As glorious as he was, right?
There was no kind of upward mobility where he could, as I say, yeah, he could see humanity was
going to surpass him. Yes. Yes. Whereas in humanity, and again, this is what we're going to be
talking about in our next two halves, right? But she...
Humans do progress.
Yeah.
And, well, here's the big reason why, because the Son of God became man.
Right.
It's all aiming at the incarnation.
The divine second person of the Holy Trinity took upon himself our human nature.
He did not take upon himself any angelic nature.
Yeah.
Yep.
And so, yes.
And so as I've now...
set a few times, that's where we're going now with the rest.
All right.
Well, we're going to take our first break
and we'll be right back in a moment.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
We talk about prayer fasting and almsgiving as the three spiritual pillars of the Orthodox
faith.
But the sad truth is that while we spend a lot of time in the church talking about prayer
and fasting, we devote relatively little time to talking about almsgiving.
Money.
What does that have to do with the gospel?
The Orthodox Christian Leadership Initiative is pleased to announce the sixth annual Orthodox
advanced leadership conference.
And this year's theme is money.
The gospel changes everything.
Parish leaders at emerging leaders
among the clergy and laity who serve the local parish,
diocese or orthodox nonprofits are encouraged
to attend either in person or online.
You can learn more information about this September 16
to 18 conference by going to orthodoxservantleaders.com.
That's orthodox.
We have to choose to recover the basic foundational understanding of the place of money and salvation.
This has been a public service announcement of ancient faith radio.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855
237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody. This is the second half of the show, and it's where we begin
to take your call, so please give us a ring at 855-AF radio. Again, that's 855-237-2346.
But before we get back to death and all of that cheerful stuff, you might have heard
that ancient faith ministries is in the process of looking for its next CEO, also known as my boss.
It should fade. John Maddox is retiring in a year and AFM is accepting applications through
Friday, July 15th for his successor as CEO. Could you be the next CEO of Ancient Faith Ministries?
Or do you know someone who could be? No media experience is required. It is an
executive leadership role. You can see the job description at ancientfaith.com slash
CO-Search.
Again, it's ancientfaith.com slash
C-E-O-Search. You can apply by sending your resume and a cover letter
describing your interest and your goals and three references to apply at
ancientfaith.com. The deadline is Friday, July 15th. So snap to it. You could be my boss.
You could order me around. It could be amazing. It's true. I wasn't talking to you
father Steven, so just... I know. Also, you're married and no man can serve
of two masks.
That's very true.
It's true.
So, all right, well, death.
Yeah.
Here we are, second half.
Right, I mean, this is a very cheery episode.
I know how many episodes we have about demons and death
in the underworld and hell and all this kind of stuff.
Were you in a morbid or like super metal?
One of the two.
Probably more morbid.
probably like it.
Old tones on tail cassette tape. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It's okay. I'm okay with that. So all right. Well, death.
Right. So, uh, before we get to death, death is coming, right? It will take us all. Yeah.
Yeah, when the main comes around, second, Donnie Cash reference for the night.
That's good. But, you know, first we're talking about the expulsion from paradise. Right? So, paradise,
as we've talked about in previous episodes is a place where where God is, it is this sort of
walled garden as house depicted and humanity is in Genesis 3 expelled from it.
So we talked about the
devil being sort of cast into the underworld humanity is expelled out into this present
world as the liturgy of Saint Basil the Great.
And so the first question is why, right?
So there's sort of, I'll just say nonsense readings of this, right?
that are well, you know, God made this one.
and they broke the rule and so he got mad and so he threw him out of his house.
Yeah.
Right.
There's just sort of a punishment, right?
Just sort of like, you know, you're going to have to go make it on your own now, kid.
Right?
Not under my roof.
And, you know, not only is any approach like...
that sort of anthropomorphizing God in the worst kind of way. But it fails to see how this story
becomes sort of paradigmatic as a pattern for the rest of the Old Testament.
So we've talked about before in terms of talking about the presence of God in the tabernacle and the
temple, right? And this of course, as we've been saying, applies equally to paradise, that
God is a consuming fire and what he just means by that is that God's holiness, right,
his presence, his holiness, consumes that which is sinful, that which is corrupt, right,
that which is wicked, right, it burns it away and consumes it and destroys it. And so to
come into the presence of God to be in the
presence of God means that either you will be destroyed, right? Or whatever is impure,
whatever is wicked, whatever is unworthy in you will get burned away. And so obviously
the second of those is the better option. But after partaking of the tree of knowledge
of good and evil.
Adam and Evele.
they've of course had already known good.
They now come to know evil.
And so they've now entered into a different sort of mode of life.
And that mode of life means that if they remain in paradise, they will be destroyed.
They will suffer the same fate as the devil.
Right.
Interrupted.
out the underworld, right? They will be like the demons if they're immortal and wicked, right?
That's what a demon is, right? And so this is the whole dialogue that God has in Genesis 3,
where he says it is not good that man should remain this way forever, right? We need to cut him
off from the tree of life so that he will not live forever. That's why he's expelled from paradise.
which some people take as being okay
Well, you've had enough so you can't have any more now because you were bad.
But really, it's it's about a change in man's mode of living
so that he does not live forever as you said.
He has to be removed from the tree of life so he doesn't persist in evil forever and be demonic.
Right.
In that state.
So this is part of the remedy.
Right.
So rather than death, there is exile.
That's the other option.
Right.
is that?
humanity is removed from the presence of God, which has now become dangerous.
Right. And this, we're going to see this play out in two weeks when we talk about the flood.
We're going to see this play out two weeks after that. When we talk about the Tower of Babel,
this plays out in terms of the entire Torah being all of the conditions and all of the means of
purification to allow humanity to draw close at least a tiny part of humanity.
to draw close again to the presence of God.
This is going to be what goes on with the destruction of the Northern Kingdom of Israel,
the exile of the Southern Kingdom of Judah.
This is going to play out through the whole Old Testament.
Before this is one of the problems that is going to be solved by Christ,
the New Testament.
But so this is intimately connected.
This is not just again a one-off story.
Right, and not communicating how people be-
came bad, but how they became mortal. Right. He said, without being able to partake of
the tree of life, humanity will not live forever. Right. And that's a good thing. Right.
Right. Right. So, you know, in this case, man's fall, and we're going to talk about meaning
several things, but in this case, man's fall means mortality. He's cast out from immortality.
cast out from the tree of life.
Right. And into this present world, which is...
characterized by corruption and death. And we've mentioned before this distinction that
St. John of Damascus makes between physical death and spiritual death. And we want to
revisit that here in the second half in a little more detail and show how the parts of
what he's saying relay and why it's important because
Sometimes, well, not just sometimes, there's a way of reading St. John of Damascus, right?
The way Thomas Aquinas read him basically.
And certain elements of like the first part of St. John of Damascus is found to wisdom
as essentially his commentary on Aristotle's categories.
So there are elements of the way he writes that invite this reading.
I don't think ultimately it's a correct reading, but you could see why people would read
him this way.
someone like Thomas Aquinas would read him this way.
And that's to read St. John as essentially
making a series of logical distinctions
about theological terms.
And this is sort of the negative tendency
that's all too prevalent in our age, even among a lot
of orthodox scholars and folks, where there's
this day.
of theology getting reduced to this kind of weird symbolic logic where it's all about
getting the right terms with the right definitions and plugging them in in the right order, right?
It's to construct the correct statements. That's what makes you, you know, orthodox or correct
theology is that you have the right. And so it's easy to go into St. John and say, okay, well,
he distinguishes physical death and spiritual death. So this is the definition of physical death.
This is a definition of spiritual, right?
And not really enter into what he's getting at
and what it means and the actual theological import of it.
Yeah, and on the other hand, of course,
you also have, I think, another modernist tendency,
which is to treat physical death as being the real death
and spiritual death as being a kind of metaphor,
like a metaphor for becoming bad, maybe.
you know, yeah, yeah, or or or worse, right? Again, if we want to go really, really modernist,
right, they, they look at this story and it's like, Oh, well, God told them in the day they
ate of that fruit, they would surely die and they didn't. So there's a problem in the
text. Yeah, right. And so then they'll say, Oh, well, you came up with this metaphorical
spiritual death to try to solve this glaring problem in the text. Mother of which is true,
Right? So...
So what what Saint John says right and and we're going to start at the level of the logical distinction he makes but we're going to go beyond that
So the logical distinction he makes is that physical death is the separation of the soul from the body
Okay, and spiritual death is the separation of the soul from God
Okay
So, that's nicely parallel.
You can see how those would both be different types of deaths.
Right, right. You can see how somebody would just treat those as propositions to plug into a
Syligism somewhere. Right. But we have to dig a little deeper because first of all, we have to
talk about what we mean by separation. Yeah, right. I mean, where exactly is God that my soul can
can be separated from him.
So it's now in a place where he's not, right?
That's, that's, you know, right.
And physical death as we've talked about, right?
When you say to someone, well, physical death
is a separation of the soul from the body.
You don't get a lot of, well, what does that mean?
But that's because there's these presuppositions.
One of which is that the soul is sort of a thing.
You mean it's not like un-ghost with Patrick's wavy?
No, it's a sphere.
Ha-ha-ha-ha-ha.
It's a floating orb.
Right, the souls of it, yeah, it's
like a force ghost or it's a ball of light or whatever, right?
It sort of comes out of someone's body and floats up into the sky or wherever it floats
or you know, gets eaten by a movie monster to power him up or whatever happens to him.
Right.
So, grab some.
So, you know, some of that in episode of Next Generation.
Yeah.
Without eating sauce.
Right.
Time traveling data.
There we go.
I can't remember the entire...
that episode now but it was actually a two-parter season cliffhanger and then the beginning
of where the wet back it met Gainin and it was on earth in the 19th century and Mark Twain
and Mark Twain yeah and the head of data the severed head of data and yeah yeah and they were
I want it there's no fition well there's the ophidian cane right right right right oh someone
would you say?
the episode is called Times Arrow.
Yeah.
Part one and two.
Thank you, Nate.
Thanks for me.
The triolic waves being generated by the creatures.
That's how they track them, though, they're visible.
Anyway, it's the point being that's not how it works.
That's not how it works.
Any of this works.
Yes.
Tales of the Cramb even died and Times Arrow both had acted
resolved tonight.
Good night, everybody.
So.
But so as we've talked.
about the soul is not a thing, right? It's not an object. It's not a ray of
I think. It is the it is the life of the body, right? And so when you see a body
that is dead, what has changed is that there's no longer life in it. Yeah, right.
And as a result of not having life in it, it begins to decompose, etc.
pretty much instantly, right? Right. But so the
life is what we're talking about when we're talking about a soul.
And so it is no less problematic to understand,
well, like what is life?
Where did the life go?
How, you know, right?
That's just as cryptic in terms of what separation means
as separating the soul from God is, right?
Neither of those is as clear cut as we might immediately think.
So, we have to go back, we don't have to go back that far.
because we're just in Genesis 3.
But we can go back a few pages and see
that where does the soul come from?
When man has created God fashions him
from the dust of the earth, his body from the dust of the earth
and then breathes the breath of life,
the breath, the spirit, the life into him.
And so
the connection between the soul and God is being established there. Right?
That the breath of life, the soul, this is portrayed here as the breath of God. Right?
So there's a connection between God and life, right? God is the living God, and that
is establishing the connection between that life and the body which it comes to and
live in. Yeah, and I recall.
I can't remember which one now, so forgive me.
But I think at least one of the Holy Fathers says in his motto for what man is composed
of, he says that man is body, soul and Holy Spirit.
You know, that man, as he's made, that God's action within him is part of what it is that
he's supposed to be, essentially.
That's my understanding of it anyway.
Yeah, and so there's this
right where God is the life of the soul and the soul is the life of the body. Yeah. Right. And so one, uh,
metaphor that I've come up with, which is a little grotesque, but deal with it.
It's a metaphor for sin and death. So I mean, where are you going to go? Right. Right.
But is
is if you think about in terms of
understanding what the separation
would then be, right?
We've established that connection, right?
God is the life of the soul,
the soul is the life of the body.
That's the connection.
So then what does the separation mean?
Right?
If you take one of your fingers or toes,
I'm not advising this by the way.
Yeah, don't do this kids.
Do not conduct this as an experiment, children.
You will regret it.
Some of us might have done it when we were younger.
And if anyone does do this...
their parents should direct their angry cards of letters to father Andrew Dane,
courtesy of ancient faith.
That's right.
But we told you not to do it.
So if you tie a tourniquet around one of your fingers or toes, right, and you cut off the blood flow.
Right. And just like, because just like Leviticus says, the blood is the life of the thing, right?
The blood is bringing the oxygen.
It's bringing the nourishment.
It's bringing the life to that member of your body, right?
If you tie a tourniquet around it, what will happen once it's cut off from the source of life?
It will die.
Yeah, right. The cells that make it up will start to die.
Eventually it will completely die. It will begin to decompose. It will become corrupt. Eventually it will literally fall off.
Right and just be gone. Right.
In the process
you will probably get a nasty case of gangrene
and that gangrene that rot may spread.
other healthy tissue. And that's gross. That is gross and painful and
fairly bad for you. You could die. Yes. Yes. But this is what makes it a good
metaphor. Yes, right. Right. Because what's being depicted here, the expulsion
from paradise, is that immediately the spiritual death happens immediately.
That spiritual death means that the souls of Adam and Eve are cut...
off from the source of their life. And so they begin to die physically. The physical death is the result.
The bodily corruption is the result. Right. And it corrupts not only them, but it corrupts the
creation around them. Until the creation around them becomes full of death. And then eventually they
physically die as a result of the spiritual death.
Right, eventually they are, they are.
Cut off right and so what that means is that
You know the the Hebrew has what's called an infinitive absolute construction when it's usually translated in English
You will surely die, but if you translated it really literally from the Hebrew it would be dying you will die
Hmm on that day dying you will die
Yes, he got both this progressive and kind of future
future sets, going on at the same time.
Yeah, and so the idea here is that the spiritual death is the real death
Yeah, tying that tourniquet between you and God
Being cut off from God as the source of life
That's what begins that's the real death because that begins the dying process of the physical death is a consequence
An image of the real death that's already happened
Yeah, and I mean, and this is what begins at this point
Adam and Eve. And this is also referred to, I have someone left us a message. And I'm going to play for us a
second here, but the sleaze to, you know, this notion of the garments of skin, right? But, you know, they put on fig leaves for a second, too. And so this is what leads to this question from our friend frequent frequent collar Kyle from
from Ireland, so here's from Kyle, this is what he had to say.
Hi, fathers. I have a question on the garments of skin in contrast to the fig leaves. Growing
up, I was taught that the fig leaves were Adam and Eve's way of trying to cover for their
sins through works, as if it's some kind of parallel to the whole of the Old Testament
and the law, whereas the garments that God made were some kind of appeasing of his anger
I'm sorry.
of justice in that an animal had to be killed and blood had to be shared in order for
salvation to truly take effect if you like. I've listened to enough of the whole
kinds of God to know that this kind of shorthand idea of appeasing God's wrath is certainly
we'll say I'm not giving the full picture so in short what are the fig leaves? What's going on with
of the fig leaves versus the garments of skin. Thank you very much.
Alright, so the first thing that I would say to that is, if it really is the case that
God killing the animals is for appeasing His wrath, then why is it that after that happens
Adam and Eve are not just welcomed back into paradise?
Because I didn't have to take care of it, but apparently not.
Right.
Yeah.
And I mean, someone could say, well, I guess in that understanding.
He described that, well, yeah, that's because the Old Testament sacrifices are ineffectual,
but why would God feel the need to do an ineffectual sacrifice?
Yeah, right, right. But I mean, there's no indication in the text
that God's wrath is a piece or something by this act. Like, it's just not said.
No, there's not even indication of wrath.
Right, right. It doesn't say, it doesn't even say, and God became angry and set onto them.
Like there's nothing like, yeah.
Yeah, this is right after it is not good
that man should stay forever in this state.
Yeah, this is a compassionate God.
Right, this is, they're being expelled
for compassionate reasons.
Yeah.
And so this is again,
to hone in on this, right?
That what we've just said about death
and how physical death works and spiritual death works
is not compatible with
the idea of God administering the death penalty people by killing them when they die.
Right. That cannot be repeated enough. And because even people who get that about Genesis,
do not get that in real life. When someone dies, who they care about, who I care about,
any of us care about. Right? Especially if they die younger.
or at a time or in a way that we don't think they should have, right? It's God killed them.
Right? That's not how it works. That's not what death is for. Right? That's not what life in this
world and death is for. Yeah, so yeah, so this is not a
death penalty, right? And so because there's no death penalty in view, applying a death penalty to an animal
is right view. Yeah, it would be irrelevant. Yeah. And I mean, we're going to go on about this
a little bit, but the idea, the garments of skin is not God killing some animals and making some leather
that, you know, for them to wear. Although it gets depicted that way, I can agraphically, because
How old would you depict this, right?
This is literary imagery, so it gets turned into visual imagery.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly.
No, it's that mankind's mode of existence now alters to become like the animals.
We're going to talk about that a little bit more, but he's mode of existence now becomes mortal.
It becomes deathly.
Right?
Let me throw in another thing.
iconography. Hold on to your chair.
I can ogre from holding on.
It's not meant to be a literal photographic recording of material reality.
But what about the community apostles icon that has two Jesus' in it?
I mean, isn't that no?
Or the the nativity icon, right?
It has like 83 different things happening all at the same time.
Right.
Yeah.
No.
Right.
I'll ask about the fake leaves in control.
the garments of skin, what is all that about?
I mean, if you had to pick a leaf though,
I have a fig tree in my yard actually.
So those are nice big leaves.
So there is that to be said about.
There you go, you can.
Yeah, they're big.
Not ready to leave this topic.
Right, so this is the importance of the fig leaves
So, so this is the importance of the fig leaves is connected to what they're...
the situation they're attempting to resolve.
So again, if you want to try to do works or works of the law or something,
then you have to somehow say that Adam and Eve went through this thought process of,
We did the thing we weren't supposed to do.
And so we need to now do good stuff.
to impress God so he won't be mad at us anymore.
And the good stuff they chose to do was cover themselves with fig leaves.
Right? See how that doesn't track?
Yeah, right. Yeah. That's not good works.
That doesn't track it off. So the situation they're trying to
resolve with is not guilt. Yeah. Right.
um guilt well i don't want to go too far down that rabbit trail but
There's nothing particularly Christian about the concept of guilt. We'll put it that way.
But so this isn't a problem of they feel guilty. This isn't a problem of them thinking now the death
penalty is going to come upon them. This is the problem according to the text is that they realize
that they're naked. They were always naked. They didn't realize they're naked.
I mean, what does that mean?
It's not like they suddenly looked down for the first time and said, wait, we're not wearing
clothes.
Hold on.
What are clothes?
Right.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Like, where would they have seen that, of clothes?
Clothes haven't been invented yet.
Yeah.
All these other animals are much furier than us.
This is embarrassing.
No.
Um, so, uh, no, this is, this is an image.
Right.
is an image of innocence and innocence lost. So little kids, right, little babies and little
toddlers will run around naked, half naked, right. They don't care. They don't think anything
of it. Most of the time their parents don't think anything of it. They get to a certain age
and that's no longer appropriate. They reach a certain level of maturity and now there's
embarrassment and shame and other issues because...
of sin in the world, right? There wasn't no sin in the world. Everybody could walk around naked.
Right. The only reason I'm pointing that out is that today is international new today.
I, you didn't know that. I didn't even know that was a thing. What it is. But anyway, I'm not
promoting nudism for the rest of the day. No. If you think I have said your angry letters too
You're funny, every day, man.
You're a care of.
You should face ministries.
But the point being there's no...
there's no sense of shame or inappropriate or anything,
until they have the knowledge of good and evil.
Right.
Now that they have the knowledge of evil,
now that evil has come into them
and in our third half we're gonna talk more about what that means,
now there are issues.
And so they go and they cover themselves
deal with the problem of being naked.
and exposed in the humiliation and the embarrassment that they now experience.
Right?
The passions they now experience.
And that's why when God comes and confronts them about it, he says, who told you you were
naked?
Yeah.
And then I love in some translations, did you eat of the tree, which I told you not to eat?
Was it me?
Was this woman you put here with me?
Right.
Very predictable.
Yeah.
But so the, this is another important distinction.
I'm trying not to pick on St. Augustine too much tonight,
but there's another important distinction
that gets kind of lost a lot of times
in Western theology where Adam and Eve are viewed as perfect.
Yeah, what does perfect mean exactly?
And so paradise is lost
and then paradise is regained, right?
The idea of salvation is going back.
the state, Adam and Eve were in. Right. Right. But that's not what's portrayed here. And this
nakedness idea is key to understanding that. Right. Adam and Eve are children, not physically,
perhaps, we don't know what they look like physically at this point. But, but they're children,
they're innocent. Right. Until they're not. And that's why the phrase, the knowledge of good and
evil, every other place where it's used in
the Old Testament, it's used to refer to a child coming to maturity.
Yeah. Right. So they jump the gun and receive this knowledge that
they're not ready for that they're not mature enough for as well. The
father say that there would have been a point at which Adam and Eve would have
been allowed to eat of that tree. When they had properly matured. Right.
This is why the book of Enix still has that tree in paradise.
So that's the issue here.
So as we talked about in the first half, man has this destiny.
Adam and Eve were at the beginning of their journey toward that destiny.
They had not arrived.
They had not even gotten started.
Right.
Really.
And then this happens.
Right.
And so that loss of innocence, that loss of their innocence is what causes the shame and
humiliation of
nakedness to become a reality because again, clothes haven't been invented yet. Clothes get
invented because of this. And so they have to go and cover themselves. So the the the garments of skin,
right? This is then tell you something different, right? So why does God kill an animal?
Yeah.
to show them what death is. Because they haven't seen that before. Right. This is a
corpse. Right. And as we just said, physical death is the image of spiritual death.
Right. And so God gives this image to them. Yeah. When I said dust, you are to dust, you
will return, right? Adam didn't remember being dust.
Right. So to make that meaningful, it has to be shown to him. Right. Yeah. And then the
garments of skin here, then is talking about the change to their bodies. Now again, we're
not necessarily talking about a change of physicality because we've talked about what body means.
Yes.
More about this. And in the third half, it's a collection of powers. Right. It's a collection
of
potentialities, right? That gets changed and becomes more like an animal.
Yeah, we don't know what the, if there's a physiological, like from our point of
view, a biological, physiological alteration, we don't know that, right? We just
know that there is this change in the way that humans, humans, physical bodies,
bodies that are our whole being works.
Because it's not like we did you.
world change. Yeah, we should we should emphasize that before this happens, human beings do have material bodies.
Yes. Right. We're created that way. It's this is not the moment that we went from being disembodied
souls to being embodied souls. Yeah, we've got we've got bodies, but we're now more like animals.
There's a lot of Christ after the resurrection still has a physical body. Yeah, exactly.
Right, he still does. Obviously there are differences.
right. If you ask me to define them on a scientific basis, I'm going to tell you to go away and
leave me alone. Yeah, because that's not what we have in Scripture. It doesn't say. And Adam
became two inches shorter and, you know, his blood turned from green to red. You know, right. But so
and and by way of sort of segue toward our third half, the animal soul, right, the animal part of
the soul is what is character of
by epithemia and Greek, by passions, by desires.
Yeah, yeah.
Right.
And so this is now something that's going to come to the fore.
And as for the rest of what has been said
about the garments of skin,
is this not recorded in the annals of this symbolic world?
It's true.
So we're about to take a break.
But before we do, we actually have a live call
from another Kyle.
So Kyle are you there?
Yes, I am.
Welcome Kyle to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
What is on your mind?
Where are you from Kyle?
We have Kyle from Ireland.
Do you have to be out from somewhere?
I am actually from Southern California.
And you're actually there at Redland actually.
Oh, that's your that's your place.
Father Steve.
Yeah.
Kyle of the inland empire.
Yes.
Wow, he's an actual Imperial.
That's great.
So Kyle, what is on your mind this evening?
I'm afraid you guys may have already answered it.
It was really about the distinguishing Adam being made of the Earth and that particular
nature as well as what could have been changed.
when we had the garments of skins put on.
Then maybe there was the ink we were given
the inco-porial nature of human beings being up the earth
and then the garments of skin was,
I think you guys are as discussing maybe a,
I was like a symbol of death perhaps or...
that how death may have entered the world
as you could elaborate a little bit more on that.
Yeah, so I mean, I,
well first I would not say that man was in caporeal
before death was given to him,
although I mean you could,
you could make, because of the way
that in caporeals use now in English,
but I mean you could make that point sort of etymologically,
right, that man didn't have the capability of being a corpse.
Right
But but usually in caporeal means without
material body so he does have a material body before all this goes down
Right he is made he is made of earth and of course he's gonna return to earth as as God says
But there's you know as we said there's a different kind of way that man's body functions now he has
the
The ability of mortality which he didn't have before and we're gonna talk about
What that?
does for us in the next half. But yeah, I mean we are still made of earth, but now that
earth kind of functions in another way that it did not before. So I don't know, Father,
did you want to add anything or correct anything in that?
Yeah. Well, it's interesting, Kyle of my hometown, that when Adam is created, the language,
If you look at it.
specific, it's that God creates him from the dust of the earth, right? And then places him in the garden,
which means it was earth from outside the garden.
Right? And since that's actually recorded, it's probably significant, right? And I think it's, it's,
It's done.
I think based on that, we should not overestimate the physical quality of the difference, right?
Because hypothetically, Adam and Eve are going to go out into this world bringing Eden
with them.
And so Adam has this intimate connection to it already.
He's not only going to be transforming himself, right?
aren't saved out of the world.
the creation is saved through our salvation and we're saved through Christ.
So I think, and we're obviously, this is where we're going in the third half,
is that we're, we'll be talking about the body specifically as this collection of powers
and potentialities and specifically about the passions and being subject to them.
the relationship.
that to the weakening of our body and our nature and our powers which are quasi not quite synonymous.
So I think we partially answered it. I think in the third half we're going to finish answering it.
Alrighty. Well, Kyle, on the whole, the expulsion from Paradise would be like if you had to leave
Redlands and move to San Bernardino or worse Fontana.
Very, very dangerous.
Montana is the land of nod, I guess, in this east of Eden.
Wow.
All right.
Well, Kyle, did that help?
Yes.
May I sneak in a quick confirmation of at least my thought process?
When we were put on the garments of skin that changed human nature?
It reflects a change in human in human nature.
nature, nature understood as being the denomace, the powers of a human being.
Yes.
All right.
Well, thanks for calling Kyle.
And I hope you'll stick around for the third half.
And we are going to go ahead and take our second break.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take
Take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirit.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing.
Secret Turning, a collection of short stories by Stephen Signari.
Behind Raskov was an icon of the descent into hell.
The little girl.
said the Rascova, and he was holding their hands like when we cross a big street. She pointed
and said, like them. Rascova looked at her shoulder at the icon, Adam and Eve and him,
taking them by the hand and said, ah, and nodded. They were all happy, the little girl told
Rascova. She looked at Naum and twirled her napkin into a blessing wand.
And, like all of us, she said and waived her little girl blessing over the
coffee hour haul. Father Noom wanted to say, and then what? But he didn't.
Dushanka, the little soul said. Then they forgot. No one wanted to ask her why.
Instead, he took some coffee. She said because they got big. Noom looked at
Reskova and then at the little girl. He said to the little soul, well, that answers
that. She just smiled and told Noom, you're silly.
Now available in paperback.
book and audiobook at store.inchantfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Are you welcome back?
It's the third half of the Lord of Spirits podcast
because as I've said in the past,
This is a show and a half.
So, right, we were talking about death, the first of the three elements of the fall of humanity,
and we just finished up talking about the garments of skin.
So, why don't we recap about exactly what a human body is?
It's been a long time since we did the body episodes.
Was that, I think that was like an early, early last year?
Am I, remember correctly?
I can't recall now off the top of my head, but I think it is earlier.
I think it is earlier this.
time or space. No, that's good.
So that's somewhere, somewhere.
That's probably helpful when it comes to doctor visits.
I like I go to a doctor.
Anyway.
Right, bodies.
Yeah.
Deathly bodies, dead bodies.
bodies.
Let them hit the floor.
No, so.
Yeah, from one perspective, if you think about it, right?
Right.
like let the bodies at the floor and it's raining men could be the same song or songs about the same event
right that's the thing. And I mean given that the time and space aren't a thing right when Whitney
Houston said I'm every woman it's all in me. Yes. Right. I'm just you know
And, or, you know, Walt Whitman, I contain multitudes.
Yes.
Right?
Walt Whit-
Whitney Houston.
I'm every woman I contain multitudes.
I believe it's pronounced Walt Whitman.
But anyway.
So yeah, so we've talked about, and I know we say this, and it's a cool phrase, but I don't
want it to just be like a nebulous mysterious phrase, right?
And we say that a body is a collection of powers.
or potentiality. So we went into it, I think when we really went into it, we were talking primarily about
God's body
in that context
and how
most of what's in Scripture is not anthropomorphism. It's that man is in the image of God and so man is
theomorphic, not the other way around. Right. But so here for our purposes, we're talking about
primarily human bodies, which is a version of a created body.
Right? And so we're talking about this collection of powers, and there's, as we just mentioned,
talking to Kyle of the homeland, that there is this sort of overlap. The Venn diagram is not a
circle, but there's a lot of overlap between the way body is under.
understood, say in the ancient Near East and even in the archaic period in Greece, and the way
nature comes to be understood later, the term of the Fesis, the term nature. And another rabbit
trail I'm not going to go down right now is the way in which the word Fesis or nature is used
in scripture because that's actually way more complicated than people think. Because it gets used
in second macabees and in...
some places, pre-new testament places in a certain way that pretty clearly doesn't correspond
to how it gets used in a lot of the new testament cases.
So anyway, that's a whole thing.
If anybody's looking for a dissertation topic, hey, there you go.
We're full of them.
You can have it for free.
They have to be written.
So might as well do something helpful with it.
Papers have to be published.
Yeah, right.
So, right.
But yes, there's a lot of overlap because of course nature, especially as the way
Aristotle defines it, is it's a collection of powers, right?
Dynamics power, right? It's a collection of powers that you have and different
Hypostasis, different
individual beings, different persons for humans, actualized different ones of those.
And that's what makes them separate independent beings.
But as you can see how that overlaps with the idea of the body as a collection of powers,
but those powers that are internal to a given created nature are aimed at something, right?
Because the being of any particular being is sort of aimed at something.
And so that's the other part of nature is that sort of aiming toward something.
So to use a non-human example.
right, and acorn has the same nature as an oak tree. Right, right, and the the acorn is sort of
aimed at becoming an oak tree. Every acorn doesn't become an oak tree, right, but that's what it's aimed at,
right, that's sort of the full maturity, right, of the acorn's nature is the tall, sturdy, mature,
full grown oak tree.
So then that consists of these various powers that are needed to get it from the acorn
you can hold in your hand to the giant oak tree that falls on your house in the hurricane.
I live in Louisiana.
So the same is true then, right?
When we talk about the human body or human nature, right, is that human are human constitution
Right. The powers that we are invested with as human that make us human are aimed at something.
Right. And it's not just a full-grown, physically adult human, right, that a baby becomes.
Right. This is what, as we were talking about in the first half, makes humans different
from angels and really all other beings.
Is that humans have a unique...
destiny, as we said. Humans have a unique aim and unique
telos and toward which we are directed. And to put a fine point on
it, that is God.
Yeah, God is the purpose of human beings. Yes. And it's
interesting. There's a line from St Gregory, the Theologians,
funeral or
for St. Basil, which is just a fancy patrology kind of way of saying, this is the eulogy that he gave at St. Basil's funeral,
where he talks about an incident where a ruler, a prefect, or somebody came up to St. Basil and joined him to engage in pagan worship.
And Basil, of course, says, are you kidding me?
Effective
But Gregory relates this as a dialogue and one of the things that Basil says in his dialogue with this prefect is
He says
You know the prefect says why why will you not you know worship our gods?
You know everybody else has has yielded whatever and he says because this is not the will of my real sovereign
Nor can I who am the creature of God and
and bitten
myself to be God, submit to worship any creature. So so basil here puts forward this idea. This
is in chapter 48, by the way, if anyone wants to look this up in his funeral, or ration
for St. Basil, that basil is a creature and he's bitten to be God and he's talking about
this, that God is his, his telos, his purpose, his aim, his target, right? And because that's
the case then he can't worship any creature.
He can only worship God if he's being true to who he truly is.
It's kind of a side remark, but it's very memorable.
This is the translation, bitten myself to be God,
or I think some translation say,
commended to become God.
This is St. Gregory quoting St. Basil in this funeral oration.
Right. Of course this has obvious residences with
the nathonacious famous, God became man so that man might become God.
Right. Right exactly.
And so that sounds really cool, but what is that?
Yeah, right. Right. So what does it mean?
So, right, what we're saying is, right, you look at the acorn,
the end of that is a full grown oak tree.
You look at a baby that was just born, right, or a sonogram of a baby
that was just conceived. Right.
Well
fairly recently or you wouldn't have a much of a son of a crown. But anyway, you get my point.
You look at that, you know, embryo, right? And that is, you know, if we're comparing that to the
acorn, the oak tree for that new human life is not an adult human. Right. The oak tree for that
new human life is God.
Yeah, that's what we're saying.
Just to put a fine point on it.
Now, again, that sounds cool.
What does that mean?
Right?
So now we're going to start using crazy terms and then go back on ourselves.
So bear with us.
This is the part where Father Stephen confuses even me.
So here we go.
So this is where I put a crowbar inside your brain pan.
and so twisted. Yeah. No. So. Okay. So I'm here for it. God is a God is the being who, right?
And I'm going to qualify all this. I know there's somebody out there who's like you just said God
is a being. I'm going there. Right. Wait for it. Okay. God is the being whose existence and essence
interco extensive.
What does that mean? Right? Yeah, right. Okay. So a simple way of saying that is that God is who he is
Yeah, he hasn't arrived there. He's not on his way there
He is who he is right. Yes. I am who I am
There is no for God. There is no acorn stage
Yeah, he's not becoming it. He's not becoming anything right right
He's not in process
Right? Okay. And when I say, even when I say that his existence and essence are co extensive,
right, I'm not saying that when we use the word existence to describe God or the word essence
to describe the divine essence, God's essence, that we mean the same thing as when we talk about
the existence or essence of me or a table or one of my heathen dogs. Right. We don't mean the same
thing. We don't...
even mean something analogical. Sorry, Thomas Quattis. It's not even an analogy. We can make
analogies between me and the heathen dog and the table. But those analogies never connect up to God.
So as St. Max's confessor said, if God exists, I do not. If I exist, God does not.
So we as orthodox Christian
could say that we don't believe God exists because what we mean by that is that what we usually
mean when we use the phrase exist, like has material reality. Like if someone says unicorns don't exist.
Right. They don't mean that the concept of a unicorn doesn't exist. They don't mean that
unicorns don't exist in fiction. They mean unicorns don't have material reality,
scientific reality in the present world.
Well, God doesn't have materials.
Yeah, you can't put him in a miserable and quantifiable
and beaker or weight, weigh him.
Yeah.
So he does not exist in that sense, right?
Right.
So what I'm actually doing, when I say that God's existence
and essence are co extensive, is actually
what we call in the Orthodox Church an apophatic move
or a negative theological move, right?
I'm saying that this is a way in which God...
is different from us. We don't know what it means to have your existence and essence
be co extensive. Right. I just know that mine aren't. Yes. Right. Yep. Right. That I am on my
way somewhere. I am constantly in flux, not goalless flux, but flux. Right. And God is not. So I'm
saying essentially what I'm saying by that statement is God is not like me or the table or my
I hear them don't.
right? Right? So or any any other creative thing, right? Including angels and demons. Yeah, I mean
this is a point that the fathers make a lot that that he's utterly unlike any creative thing that the
uncreated one is not there's no you know we have language to describe him right? We have language
from scripture and that's the safest place to go right is to quote scripture, but it does not
encapsulated
him or define him. Right. You know. Right. Yeah. And so that was in prep to try not to break anyone's
brain with what I'm about to do. But I think it kind of broke father Andrew's brain earlier. So
yes. No promises. Okay. So I think I might get it now. I'm working on it though. I'm working on it.
I'm learning.
I'm becoming it.
Yes.
See, there we go.
It's coming close.
or two. So, when we're existence and essence here, we're using existence to refer to sort
of the present state of our day to day flux and growth and change and generation and corruption
and all of those fluxes that we're in, right? And essence then has to do with identity
with who and what we are. Right? So...
A way to talk about this that is obviously very applicable to Genesis 1 through 3.
The language of Genesis 1 through 3 that's related to this is about the image of God.
Hmm.
Right.
And in the way we've talked about it on this show before.
So on one hand, humanity is created in the image of God.
Right.
And that set is a statement.
That's a statement of assets.
Right? That is an essential statement about humanity. Right.
What humanity is. Totally apart from what happens in the garden.
Right. Totally apart from the existence of any given human. Right.
This is the plan. And that's why it's broadly, that's why it's broadly applied.
Right. So after the flood, he who spills man's blood, his blood shall be spilled by man
four in the image of God, God made man.
Right, from every human...
no matter how miserable a cuss they are,
no matter how wonderful they are,
no matter how ravaged by sin they are,
they're still in the image of God in this sense.
They are essentially human still, right?
So there's image of God in that sense, right?
Then there is our existence that we've talked about
in the show how imaging God has this verbal sense.
in which imaging God is something we do.
Right.
Able to do.
And this is related to
theosis, participation in God's grace,
participation of our energies
that we actively do the things that God does.
Right.
Energy is our working in the world, working in creation.
God is working in creation.
We cooperate and participate in his-
work in creation, right? And so we image him, right, within the creation. Okay, so that's
that's like our existence. And the eventual product of that continued imaging, right, where
that imaging is aimed, its goal would be what the Father's called the likeness, right,
of God, right?
And people...
will quickly point out to you if they've studied the Old Testament and they've
studied Hebrew, they will try to offer this as a critique of the church
fathers and say, oh, they didn't know Hebrew because if they knew Hebrew, they
know that image and likeness as they're used in in Genesis here are synonyms.
They knew that.
The point, the image in which we're created is...
is also the goal. Right. Because we are becoming because we're not just being. Because they're
both God. Yeah. Right. The image of God and the likeness of God. Yeah. And so like the human
identity as we were made to be is something that is always in the future. Because we being
finite will never arrive.
at being God. Right. Our identity is always in the future. Our existence is who I am today.
Right. And between who I am today and that identity in the future, there is this lack or this gap
or this expanse or this nothingness, if you really like John Paul's art. I don't. Almost nothing
You
It was one of the worst experiences I had in high school was reading.
What's your idea, Dodja?
You know, we read, we clothe, you know, no exit in French.
Because it was French class.
And I was like, why are we reading this?
Let me submit to you.
If you had to live your whole life in France,
you would probably also think hell is other people.
Oh, no, come on.
Okay.
So, I kid the French.
I would like to visit France someday.
I live among many of them.
They're all exiles.
I live...
Right, right, right.
Right.
So, and I'm a little bit French Canadian, by the way.
A little bit my great-grandmother,
her maiden name was Tibo.
So they go.
Yeah, yeah.
I might be related to that guy who talks about symbolic stuff.
I can't remember his name though.
Okay.
So there's, right, so there's this gap,
there's this lack, right, between me and it.
and that will
never collapse, because as we were just saying, the distance, again, we're using spatial
terms metaphorically, between who I am and who God is, is infinite.
Yeah.
And remains infinite, even as I continue to change and move toward it, it remains infinite,
which means that even when there's another place we have to break our
brain. Even when we're in the life of the world to come, we're not going to be in a static state.
Right. Right. Which also implies that if our progress is always this point in the future, future
for us, right? Which is the fullness of the stature of Christ, right? To use St. Paul's language.
Right. Uh, then that means that
this modern thing that we see now,
identitarianism, right, where people take these labels
and apply them to themselves.
And then that becomes the end all be all of how they conceive
of themselves, you know, looking for their identity either
in something in the past or something at this moment, right?
And I'm not saying not, you know,
we shouldn't respect the past and understand tradition.
I don't talk about history.
I'm talking about a identitarianism.
It's really an anti-Christian philosophy.
We can't answer.
fundamentally kind of an unhopeful philosophy because it means I've arrived. I am this thing,
and this is who I and what I am, period. The becoming is not on the table. It's a distortion.
Really. And one way, one devastatingly destructive way in which we are faithful to something other than
Christ, right?
is when we're faithful to some version of ourselves.
We have this idea that we're not allowed to break character.
That whoever I was yesterday,
I have to be someone consistent with that today.
Even if who I was yesterday was wretched and miserable.
This is just who I am.
You can be better.
Right, I can't make a break.
And that is, this is something I say to people over and over and over.
again in confession, right? Is that the devil doesn't spend his time trying to get us to
sin. We do that on our own. Right? The devil spends his time when we fall telling us not
to get up. Right. Telling us that this is where we belong. This is who we are. Don't
bother trying to do better to be better to make any progress. Why? Because the thing he's
He's hated about humanity since the very beginning is that we're capable of making that progress.
Yeah.
And he hasn't changed because he can't.
Right.
As we have said in the past.
So he continues to come with this same thing.
Right.
But the fact is we have the church gives us countless opportunities to make these breaks.
When we're baptized, when we're received into the church, every time we come to confession.
Right.
chance to.
make a new start and continue to make this progress.
That will potentially go on forever,
that even the angels have not been blessed
with the possibility of.
Yeah.
Right.
Yep.
And so this, everything we just said,
about this progress, about becoming like Christ,
because of course Christ is the person
Right in whom humanity
is fully and completely united to God.
Yeah, he's the real man.
He's the total man.
So everything we've just said was true of Adam and Eve before they ate from the tree
in the same way it's true of us now.
Yep.
They were at the beginning of this same journey of theosis that we are on.
You
because of the expulsion from paradise
and because of death,
and because of what happens there,
there's now this second complicating factor.
And that stems from what we were discussing
at the end of the second half regarding the garments of skin.
And it's gonna lead us into the nature of repentance.
Because what you'll find, right, especially when you see the fathers responding to certain
things in St. Augustine, or just the fathers speaking in general about the expulsion from
paradise and how human nature changed, changed right, right again, nature being like body,
being this, this collection of powers.
What they're going to talk about is they're going to talk about our nature being weakened.
Yeah, we can be acted upon. We're passable passable. P.A.S.S.I.B.L.E.
Right. Yeah.
And that I know there's a legion of Calvinist out there who are going to say, you don't really believe
in sin. Oh, that's wishy-washy. Right. We're going to talk about sin next time.
But yes, but the
Here is the key here is that becoming possible makes a subject to the passions
Yeah, right and and there's there's what we call blameless and blame worthy passions and
Blameless passions are the things that we the weaknesses that we suffer from
Simply by virtue of being human so getting tired. Yeah by virtue of being humans in mortal bodies. Yes
excuse me correct right let's be very
by virtue of the type of body, the type of nature we have now
in this world outside the garden.
The kind of thing when we say I'm only human,
I'm only human in a mortal body.
Right, so we get tired, we get hungry, we get thirsty,
we have desires, right, for things
that are not sinful in another themselves.
We get cold, we get hot, we get that we're rated, we get.
Right.
Which you probably get all those things
being in Louisiana in the summer.
So all at once.
That's true.
Um, yeah.
How can I be so dehydrated when it's so humid?
Some are more easily satisfied than others.
Like there's plenty of good food around getting cool is a lot harder.
Yeah.
But then even these blameless passions, if we indulge them can become more of the passions,
right?
So getting tired, fatigue, that can turn into laziness, right?
If you choose that as
your way of being, or like hunger can turn into gluttony, like you just can't have enough.
Right.
Or, you know, the normal natural desire between husbands and wives can turn into lust.
Like all these kinds of things.
And that's, you know, that's what's going on.
And it, of course, intensifies with the blameworthy passions and intensifies the, the passivity
that could take you over.
acted upon, you're no longer...
control of yourself. You're out of control. We use this language. Yeah. And those are things like
the blameworthy passions, kind of some obvious things like greed, like pride, like envy, like
wrath, and anger, desire for revenge, right? Those aren't like excesses of good things,
right? Right. Or excesses of unavoidable things. Those are just bad things. Yes. Right.
right? Right, the tender multiply from these, yeah, right exactly, exactly. And we
I should say, you know, we actually got a couple of questions.
There were a couple of people who called, I wasn't sure exactly what they were calling
about, to be honest, but then also some questions we got in one of the chats on YouTube about
Christ and his mortal human body, right?
He voluntarily accepted the blameless passions, but he remained in control of them.
So like he got hungry, but he was never gluttonous.
Right.
Right? And it's it's
noting it's worth no we we have to be a little careful here right so
Christ's human nature was not a fallen human nature yes cannot underline that
enough right what does that mean right well we've just talked about what that
means that means it was not weakened in that way right so when we talk about
that's why that word voluntary is so important.
Right. Christ voluntarily gets tired. He voluntarily sleeps. He voluntarily eats and drinks. Right.
And can be killed. Well, no. He can't. He voluntarily dies. Right. That's what I'm saying. He voluntarily.
Is it? Yes. Someone asked the question like, how is this different from suicide?
And I said, well, in the scripture, it says that he lays down his own life. He says that.
The dnaunt
takes it from him, but he lays down his life, which is not the same thing as I kill myself.
Right. He has the power to lay down his life and to take it up again.
And to take it up again.
And he has that because he is not possible, right?
Because he is not naturally subject to these things the way we are.
Right.
He is able to voluntarily submit to them.
Yeah.
Yeah, so gotta be careful there.
Although if you still think I'm a heretic
and pressure letters to Father Andrew Damien.
There you go.
To beat, to beat.
But this mortality and the mutability that brings
that passability is also what allows for repentance.
For the process of healing and change
and strengthening.
right of those powers, right, that takes place within this mortal life, right, that we have in
this world, to which Adam and Eve are sent. They're sent into this world to live a mortal life that
will end with death, right? And then from there, after the resurrection of Christ, to enter into the
the life of the world to come, right? So our mortal
life then, part of the problem with sort of at least American and probably Western folk religion,
which is sometimes only vaguely Christian is that human life is presented as if this life on this
Earth is the whole ball game. And then once it's done, if you did the right things,
However, those are conceived, whether it's just being a good guy or believing certain principles
or whatever it is depending on who you're talking to.
Then you go to heaven and you're just happy and have a great time for eternity.
And if you do the wrong things or fail to do the right things, then you go to hell and
suffer and get tortured for all eternity.
And so everything is focused on this life.
But if we understand this the way the scriptures teach and the way the fathers teach
Then this mortal life and the whole aspect of repentance and dealing with sin is sort of this parenthesis
Right, it's this speed bump that enters in on the road of theosis
Yeah, on the road of the destiny of human persons, right. It's a setback
Right, like tempest keep
It's only a setback.
It's a setback, I would dig it in the crates on that one,
where it pauses on our journey, right?
But so if we're living the Christian life,
the way it's set out for us by the church, right?
They were essentially progressing on two fronts
during this mortal life.
We are not only dealing with the parenthesis,
not only dealing with through...
repentance, right? The passions to which we've become subject and the damage that's been done.
But we're also on the other side experiencing fiosus, right? And we're drawing closer toward
that human destiny, again within the Christian life. We're doing both of those at the same time.
Yeah, that repentance is, we're going to talk about this a little bit more in just a second
I think but the repentance is
not just I did something bad and it needs to be fixed, although that's an element, right?
If you did something bad, it needs to be made right.
But it's also this pressing towards becoming more like Christ and progressing in faithfulness,
which is not just a matter of stop doing bad things.
It's doing more worship, more love, right?
So, so yeah, it's as you said, it's not just dealing with the setback. It's it's also
progress getting back on the track heading back in the direction of Christ. Right and
Yeah, both of those are active. Yeah. Yeah. Neither of those is a passive thing. Right exactly
Theosis is not like I get my theology worked out better
Right, the right ideas and I get rid of the bad ideas. I believe the right things. I can't just sit at home and do theosis
I tweet the right.
hashtags, right? Like, right?
Nor is, right? As you were saying, nor is repentance. A lot of times,
repentance, we don't even think we have to fix it, right? A lot of times with
repentance is I said, I was sorry. Yeah, I did something bad and God's mad at me
or I did something bad and these other people are mad at me. And so I need to go
apologize and get them to not be mad at me anymore. That's the problem.
Right right right having having read and being in the process of
raising four children. I have occasionally seen, I'll just say the younger ones, sometimes
will, you know, especially when they're quite young, pummel one another. And then immediately
say, sorry. You know, I said I was sorry. You hit him. Right. Right.
You try not to laugh where they do that. But if that's what repentance was, then Adam and
Eve could have just done it. Right. Golden dudes. Right. I could just said we're really
sorry that was dumb
you're right. You know. And you don't find even if you go and read like the various versions of
the life of Adam and Eve that describes their repentance, their repentance is like Adam standing
in the Jordan River for 40 days. Right. They seem to think there are things they have to do. There's
some process here. Wait, are you saying that faithfulness without works is dead? Yes. I feel like
I'm saying people this includes works.
Yeah, right.
But I'm saying believe.
things without works is dead. Yes, super dead. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Cause there's no life in it. Yes. Yeah. Right. As we've been using death tonight. Right. So what we have is not God getting mad and applying punishments and then because of some internal standard of justice within God, he has to enact an elaborate plan to allow himself to not be mad at people anymore.
So he can let them back into paradise. I don't know that's reductionist, but I'm sorry a lot of
folks believe that. But you really boil it down. Yeah. Right. That's not what we see depicted here.
What we see depicted here is a chain reaction of consequences from which from the very beginning
God is trying to rescue us. Trying to save us from ourselves. Trying to save us from the death
destruction that's brought about by our own.
actions. So that once that's been dealt with and we've been restored, we can get back on track
with what he created us for in the beginning, which is to share his life with him forever.
And all of that involves action going out and doing good, going out and doing what God is doing
in the world.
the Lord says, I mean, how many times does this appear in scripture?
If you love me, keep my commandments.
I mean, I don't remember how many times those things are two things are brought together.
Like it's a bunch, both old and New Testament.
If you love me, keep my commandments.
If you love God, you will keep his commandments.
Right.
And what are the things God is doing in the world?
Well, we've just said a couple of them.
One of them is, right, he's trying to save us from the death and destruction.
They're the consequences of our actions.
So one thing we need to be doing in the world is trying to help others
be rescued from the death and destruction that are the consequences of their actions and
arms. Right. And this is why the whole phariseic angle of judgment doesn't work.
Right. Because doesn't bring people to engemining someone and abandoning them to the
consequences of their actions is the opposite of what God does.
If you understand it correctly, but you can see how, if the way you understand what happens
in the expulsion for paradise, is that God punishes humans with death for disobeying
one of his commandments, then you can see how someone could become a Pharisee.
This person is miserable and deserves to rot and go to hell because of all the sins
they've committed.
than but as per
Anishis is that is and as much as we like to deride those people, right?
And it's always other people.
It's worse when we direct it at ourselves.
When we turn around and say, I deserve to rot and go to hell because of all the things I've done.
Yeah, I can't remember.
I didn't want to say something the effect of, you know, the demons always whisper to lies.
One is, you're doing great.
And the other one is
is you there's no hope for you.
Yeah, right.
And I mean, those are the roots of, I don't know,
I've heard confessions for a well over a decade and a half now.
I'm pretty sure those are the roots of basically most sins.
Yeah, yeah.
And that's what the devil's been saying right from the beginning.
Yeah, because he's a big liar.
Yeah, so that's it.
So we have to understand this correctly.
And then that allows us to act as God acts.
And we can act like St. Paul says he did to the Ephesian elders where he says he never stopped night
and day with tears begging them to be reconciled to God. If we approached all of our enemies and all
of the sinners in the world, including ourselves in that way, the world would be a very different place.
Yeah. And you know, repentance then, it's not, it's about purification, right?
from the passions and all of...
their effects, it's not just about don't do bad things anymore, but actually being purified.
Right. And so I mean, sometimes people ask, well, what's the point of all the prayer
and the fasting and stuff? It's like, well, to purify us, to prepare us for the banquet,
to prepare us for that intimacy of receiving Holy Communion. Right. So we engage in these
actions of purification and why it's dangerous then to go and to receive the sacraments
without these acts of purification. It's not that you need to become worthy, because
There's no one.
ever worthy, how many of our pre-communium prayers say, I'm unworthy, but to become ready,
right, to be adequately prepared to receive. There's never a point at which you deserve,
right? But you can be purified so that you can enter in. You can do the things that God said to do
so that you can enter in and become then more like Christ through that experience of communion,
and especially holy communion of the Eucharist itself.
Yeah, yeah, I you know, I'm reminded of course in where where see Paul says in Philippians,
he says, you know, I press on toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God
in Christ Jesus. Of course, there's several different, you know, or the high calling,
I think is what the KJV has, right? What a beautiful sort of summary that is, right? Of
where he's headed and what the point is. There's no point in which he said, look, I'm a saint,
I'm gonna possible. I'm there you guys.
Right?
Yeah.
So, all right.
Well, let's have some closing thoughts.
You know, I think that the Orthodox Church is teaching about what death is as we've gone
through now, it's shown in Scripture.
It can be surprising, right?
because our cultural theology is
It's a fuse with the side of the...
death is a punishment from God. Like you messed up so bam, you're going to die now, right?
But as we said, you know, it's death is actually a gift. Death is a gift from God.
Now it comes with a lot of problems, right? We become mutable in all kinds of ways that are not
particularly comfortable, like, you know, dying.
getting sick, dying, aging, all these kinds of things.
But if we understand that the mutability that comes with death,
that is, in a sense, what death is, is actually a tool that's been added to our toolkit,
then it's a profoundly hopeful realization, I think, that, you know,
you know, St. Isaac the Syrian, for instance, said,
you've been, you know, this life has been given to you for repentance.
don't waste it on, I can't remember the rest of the line, but like,
frivolous pursuits or something like that.
Yeah. And so, what does that mean, right? This life is given to us for repentance.
It's that we've been given this tool of mutability, of mortality, of changeability.
And now, mind you, we don't know exactly how that works in a kind of a
mechanistic way like why is it that mortality makes repentance?
possible. We don't know, but this is what the Holy Father say, and it is what we see demonstrated in
Scripture. And it is essentially what God is giving Adam and Eve there at the end of chapter 3 of Genesis.
Since that we have that, then we should use it. And one of the reasons, and you know you made this
point earlier, Father, it is a profoundly hopeful thing because it means that I am not stuck with
this is just who I am.
I'm not stuck with that. I do not have to be tomorrow what I was today. I don't have
to be today what I was yesterday. I can change. Now, I can change for the worse. I've
done that many times in my life. Or I can also change to be more like Christ. I can change
to become more likely angels. I can change to become a saint. This possibility exists
for every human person and the reason
why we can change is because of this mortality that we have.
Again, we don't know exactly how it works,
but that is what it is, right?
That is what mortality is.
It's a gift from God.
And so, many of us in our lives are driven
by all kinds of desires and ambitions and pursuits, right?
We have things we want to build.
We have families, careers, our homes,
our social networks, whatever.
And many of these things are
right? They're good. You know, not a reambition or desire is bad. But if we can take the investment
that we put in that and reinvest it and place it in the life in Christ, all those other
pursuits can be sanctified and can come along right on that. But if we aim at those created
experience.
as an achievements, rather than putting our goal to be Christ, then we'll lose all of it.
You know, C.S. Lewis, not an Orthodox writer, but nonetheless, he said some good things.
He made this comment in one of those books. He said, if you aim at heaven, you will get earth thrown
in. If you aim at earth, you will get neither. And if we place all of that desire,
that we tend to put in all these things that we spend so much time trying to build. And again,
they may be good. If we put that in the goal that is Christ, if we put that in our salvation,
then the whole world is lit up with this beautiful light as it stands out in relief, you know, from
from the darkness of this world,
and all then becomes finally realized.
Christ. There is an unconquerable hope that we have. I mean the Lord spoke about this, right? He said,
you know, in this world you're going to have trouble. But we have good cheer for I have overcome the
world. And if we are aiming at Christ, if Christ is our goal, if we are, as St. Basil said,
to be God and we make that who we are.
then we will have that good cheer, that joy, Christ's joy will be given to us.
Whatever is going on in the world, right? And this is the gift of God to us in
mortality. But we only have it while we're in this life. Once your soul separates
from your body, once the life of your body has gone out, you don't have it anymore.
So, this is the opportunity now.
Today is the day of salvation.
Father?
So I think sort of the last distinction we made in the third half is very important in a
whole bunch of ways, understanding a whole bunch of things, but one of them at least,
and I'm talking here about the distinction between sort of the destiny of man and theosis,
the way in which every human person.
is biddened to become God, that God is the end, the tellos of humanity, the sense of what our
existence is, is aimed toward. That on the one hand and then on the other hand, our ongoing battle
with the passions are ongoing efforts for sort of self mastery in the face of them and of repentance
and healing.
That distinction, I think, helps us really understand why the various other religions, philosophies
of the world, seem sometimes to have some kind of purchase.
If we only have the struggle within the struggle with the passions, the goal of repentance,
the self mastery of the
That's all we have in view in terms of salvation.
Then it can be very confusing when we look at
these other philosophies and religions in the world
because it seems like
will some of these seem kind of helpful
and some of the people who are advanced
in these philosophies or religions
seem to be doing better with some of these things
like in terms of patience and self-control
and even kindness and gentleness, right?
These things that we say are fruits of the spirit.
They seem to be the head of me.
me, right? And they're not Christians. And it is true, right?
Pursuing stoicism will help you gain a certain degree of self-mastery.
Will help you resist temptations to anger. It will help you in various ways navigate
right this world, you know, say, been Freud. Complete atheist can come and tell you, you know,
these drives with the
humanity, you know, the death drive, driving you toward death and destruction. These sexual
drives, these drive that you have to, you know, contend with and help you uncover them and see how
they're working in your life. It's like, oh, therapy can lay these things out for you. All of these
philosophies and religions can help you in various ways navigate this life in this world.
But again, that's a parenth...
They're able to do that because as humans we could observe this world and life in this world and
ourselves and how they work and come to some level of understanding. But none of those things can
move us an inch toward our destiny in Christ. None of those things can take us beyond what we now
now called human. Which is this.
weakened, prone to sin, fallen humanity of this world.
None of them can take us beyond that.
None of that can align our will and our human powers and abilities with what God is doing in
the world. They can't even reveal what God is doing in the world. They can only reveal what we
are doing in and to ourselves.
And so this really points us to the uniqueness of Christ.
There is a certain utility to all manners of philosophy and thought and even human religions,
even the ones that are worshiping demons, right?
There will be people with valid insights into human behavior within this world and what
bring success in this world.
But again, none of them show us what it means for our humanity to be perfectly united to God.
And none of us will give us the means of pursuing it.
And none of them will reveal to us the love that God pours forth day to day upon his entire creation.
None of them will reveal to us the way to make the peace that is the peace of God,
the piece where there's no such thing as an enemy.
come to be in the world. None of them will show us what true kindness, what true
generosity, what a self-control and self-mastery looks like that is aimed toward
becoming something better than what we now call human. So it's only in Christ
that we can become fully human. It's only in Christ that the goal...
for which humanity was created can be seen, let alone achieved. And we need to set our
sites beyond just making it through this day without yielding to all the manifold temptations
that I've fallen to in the past, and to actually being faithful to encountering and becoming
more like Christ.
We've set our
our sites too low for too long.
And we've put way too much emphasis on what's in the
parenthesis, what's in the footnote, rather than what's in
the real story that's being told.
Those are my final thoughts.
Um, well, that is our show for today.
Thank you for listening everyone.
If you didn't get through to us live, we'd still love to
hear from you.
email us at lor-
of Spirituals.nationfaith.com. You can message us at our Facebook page or leave us a
voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of Spirits.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm
Eastern 4pm Pacific.
And if you are on Facebook, you can like our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews
and ratings everywhere. But most importantly, please share this show with a friend whom you
know is going to love it. And finally
be sure to go to www.AxioFate.com.skorksupport and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters
stay on the air and thank you to our periodic guest tonight, Mexican radio station.
Thank you.
Good night and God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 and thousands of thousands
Saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches.
and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.
Are you curious about the Orthodox Christian faith?
Do you have questions?